this is the just announced Samsung
Galaxy Z flip 5 and when you first look
at it it doesn't make any sense compared
to Samsung's very highest end phones
which can be had for like the same price
now every camera is smaller and less
capable you can expect your battery to
take longer to charge and deplete about
20 faster there's less room for calling
so the chip won't perform as well and
yeah this is more compact it folds right
well not really I mean it is shorter but
it is also thicker so the actual volume
being taken up is about the same and yet
even with all of this
why am I drawn to the z-flip 5 so much
why is it that my curiosity was so
sparked when I saw that first one or
that I very nearly switched over to it
when I tested the z-flip 4 last year and
that now we have the five I've decided
that I'm actually going to try and use
this thing on a day-to-day basis well
let's start with what's new the storage
has doubled from 128 gigabytes to 256.
although the price has also gone up too
so that's not really a perk the build
though is a win it's thinner for
starters about two millimeters thinner
when folded up but the best part of this
is how they've achieved that thinness
it's a new hinge one that for the very
first time on a Samsung flip can praise
the Lord close without a gap well
there's a tiny little hole here but it's
basically gapless and this
big deal because it's not just that it
looks better and it's a less weird shape
and it takes up less space but it also
creates less room for rogue particles
and pocket dust to just find their way
inside which trust me use any folding
phone for a period of time is a problem
and it's probably also one of the main
causes of you just ending up with a
scuffed inner screen no matter how
careful you think you're being speaking
of which this inner screen is now 25
more resistant to scratches and the
outer body is protected by armor
aluminum and Gorilla Glass victus 2
which I'm told Has the strength of
ceramic which is pretty cool considering
that ceramic has long been reserved for
the highest end luxury phones because of
its scratch resistance the only thing I
don't like and this has kind of been an
ongoing pet peeve of mine is that when
you open the phone it doesn't snap into
that fully open position it's still just
like a tiny bit flaccid which also means
a tiny bit bent they really should make
it so that opening it feels just as
tactile and satisfying as closing it
because that is fun but then the screen
is I would say not just a big but the
biggest jump since the very first flip
specifically this cover screen I mean
just compared to Samsung's last phone it
is 278 bigger it now looks like a folder
and it can do a lot more used to be able
to have a peek at your notifications
check your calendar and make a quick
voice recording but we're talking like
10 20 of the overall functionality of
the phone now
I'd call it 50. there's 13 different
widgets available at launch and they say
there's more on their way and
essentially each one is its own home
screen you swipe between them and if you
want to move quickly you pinch out and
you pick the one you want plus you can
swipe to the left to check your
notifications and down to fiddle with
quick settings it's all very smooth and
Slick for what is effectively a
secondary custom operating system on the
same phone and the other thing that I'm
noticing about the way this whole thing
is Being Framed is that it's all about
the personality Samsung's not really
trying to pitch this front screen as a
way to quickly check things it's more as
a tool for self-expression and that it
achieves I actually cannot believe how
much you can customize it everything
from the battery percentage indicator to
how to display notifications to the
exact shade of color that you want and
in what way it fades to another color
you could absolutely lose yourself in it
and I plan to do exactly that side note
you can also see how much Samsung is
pushing this whole fashion angle here
with the sheer number of cases being
offered including these rather fancy
smart ones that when applied will sync
the wallpaper on your phone and even
your Galaxy watch to match plus you can
now use apps on the front not all apps
which Samsung could have allowed you to
do but I guess they want you to only use
the apps that have been specifically
optimized to make the most of this
strange folder-like shape so there's
only like 10 at launch the screen is now
big enough though to get a full qwerty
keyboard on which means you can also
message it's a little fiddly but
completely usable with one hand which is
a luxury that I almost forgotten was
even possible okay there's a couple of
things that I do don't like not you I'm
so sorry Milo's been replaced by his
chunkier London counterparts there's
still a crease on this main display they
say it's improved but it's still very
noticeable and I just think doesn't
exactly scream hey I'm a market leading
fifth generation product and then while
this inner panel is a 120 hertz display
that can ramp its refresh rate all the
way down to one Hertz the cover screen
which is my other gripe is locked at 60.
and so what this means is that even when
you're trying to use it in this super
low power always on State this screen is
refreshing like 60 times more than it
needs to so it wastes battery there's an
upgraded chip the Snapdragon 8 Gen 2 4
Galaxy which is basically the same
Snapdragon chip you see in all top end
Android phones this year but with a
little boost to how fast it runs I'm
actually quite excited about this not
because the phone necessarily needs it
more because these flip phones feel so
perfect for game emulation which I plan
to do a lot of and is super demanding
and then this chip also has a slightly
tweaked image signal processor which
allows the phone to take the data from
the camera and process it in a way that
Samsung likes and that is the final key
upgrade the cameras not so much in terms
of Hardware I mean there's a new lens
that's a little bit clearer and reduces
sunflowers but it's more the software
you can double tap the power button to
bring it up immediately you've got new
portrait modes and better quality
portrait modes you can mess around with
zoom when you're on the cover I couldn't
do that before plus you've just got more
space to see yourself and frame your
shot properly so while the z-flip 5
might not feel as ambitious as
Motorola's Razer 40 Ultra and its edge
to edge cover screen or the crease-free
folding design of oppo's N2 flip at the
same time you can't say Samsung's
resting on their Laurels doing nothing
this is a big upgrade and this company
is still widely regarded as having the
best foldable software with this
launching on Android 13l the very latest
with a promise of four full years of
major Android updates and the most
seamless integration of foldable
features into third-party apps like just
for example this thing has a camera
feature that tracks your face to always
keep you in the middle which is already
cool for making like an Instagram reel
but then the feature can factor in when
you fold the phone adapt around it so
that you can still see yourself in the
top half and then even work natively
within these other apps like Instagram
so you can even go live using it so you
have a level of continuity here that
others are still catching up with oh
yeah and the flex mode is updated so
when you fold up an app that supports it
everything adapts so that you can
control your entire phone using just the
lower half all of this stuff is cool it
makes the most of what the phone is but
none of it really explains why the phone
even exists in the first place why is it
that people keep paying this premium to
compromise on specs for a phone that
takes up basically the same volume
according to Samsung's 70 of the
customers buying foldable phones are
choosing this flip style over the
technically higher end fold style are
they crazy well
no but what is crazy is that we overtook
Samsung and subscribers a long time ago
and we're now this close to overtaking
Apple so this Hub to the channel would
be
it's ambitious
quite proud of though I would say
there's five key things that make this
flip as surprisingly appealing as it is
the first and the most obvious is the
style I'm not gonna lie to you this is
fun flicking it open for something
important snapping it shut to end a call
there's a big part of it that feels
almost toy like and it's such a unique
prospect that if you like it there's a
good chance you're gonna love it and if
you love it you're gonna be willing to
overlook a lot of other things to make
it work and thankfully while the cameras
are one of those things that you will
have to forgive because there's no way
you can fit a modern large camera sensor
into the depth of one of these halves
they do also benefit from the ability to
fold in that you can use the same set of
pretty good cameras for both the rear
and the front so if we say that the
Galaxy s23 Ultra has a 10 out of 10
camera system on the rear then its
selfie camera is about a five whereas
with the Z flip you're getting a seven
on both with full 4K 60 frames per
second video plus the ability to use the
bass as a sort of baked in stand to prop
the phone up at whatever angle you want
but it's the mindfulness that this phone
can give you that is what really
interests me the fact that you can just
keep the phone folded up and you know
that you're reachable but still distance
from your distractions is for me a game
changer and so I really like that here
even though the cover screen is now more
capable and can do a lot of technically
full screen phone things Samsung's done
this with an understanding that the
objective is not just to make the front
screen like the inner screen because I
mean if they're the same thing then what
would be the point in unfolding it so
instead what you can do here is decide
on the inside which apps you want to
allow yourself access to on the outside
this is brilliant so the way I'm going
to set mine up for example is to allow
maps and WhatsApp and anything I might
need but keep away anything I might want
as you know a lot of people like to have
two separate phones one for work one for
pleasure this one flip phone is kind of
like having both of those but folded
into one it creates this really distinct
separation between a device that is
simple and functional and not
distracting when folded up to advice
that when you finish your work and you
just want to chill out it's expansive
and enjoyable and indulgent it makes it
feel like a window into your social
medias and your connected life without
being a door that you can just stroll
through and get lost in before you've
realized what you're doing plus I
actually like the fact that when someone
calls while you're in this folded
position it'll automatically go to
loudspeaker which really suits this
whole hands-off vibe and that if you
want to silence it you don't even need
to pick the phone up if you just place
your hand on top kind of like
suffocating it the battery also benefits
from this being a flip phone I mean it
sounds bad on the face of it this is a 3
700 million power cell in a market full
of phones packing five thousand but
thanks to efficiency improvements you
can get an extra hour versus last year's
flip 4 and if you are actually planning
to use a good mix of both the inner
screen and the outer screen then because
the outer screen is so small you'll save
a lot of battery there and finally there
is the compactness which as I've already
said I think is a little overrated I
mean the volume difference between this
and say this is negligible but there is
one distinct benefit to being short and
stubby like this women's clothing it's
anyone I met my fiance a few years ago
that it dawned on me just how little
depth there is in women's jeans and
women's workout leggings so it fixes
that let me know if you have any burning
questions about this phone I'll answer
as many as I can and I will catch you in
the next one